<!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?-->
<node_export created="Wed, 05 Apr 2017 12:07:29 -0300">
	<node>
		<nid>10</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Collaborators</title>
		<p><a href="http://www.physics.ryerson.ca/user/112" target="_blank">Alexandre (Sasha) Douplik</a>, Department of Physics, Ryerson University<img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/collaboration.jpg" style="float:right; height:300px; width:400px" /></p>

		<div><a href="http://web.physics.ryerson.ca/mkolios/index.html" target="_blank">Michael Kolios</a>, Department of Physics, Ryerson University</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="http://ibbme.utoronto.ca/faculty/core-faculty/ofer-levi/" target="_blank">Ofer Levi</a>, Institute of Biomaterials and Biomedical Engineering, University of Toronto</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="http://www.mie.utoronto.ca/faculty/profile.php?id=32" target="_blank">Andreas Mandelis</a>, Mechanical and Industrial Engineering, University of Toronto</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="http://www.tomowave.com/alexander-oraevsky.html" target="_blank">Alexander Oraevsky</a>, Tomowave Laboratories Inc., Houston, Texas&nbsp;</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="http://www.massey.ac.nz/massey/expertise/profile.cfm?stref=618250" target="_blank">Chris Riley</a>, Department of Health Management, Atlantic Veterinary College, UPEI</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="http://medbio.utoronto.ca/faculty/vitkin.html" target="_blank">Alex Vitkin</a>, Ontario Cancer Institute, Princess Margaret Hospital, Toronto</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<p><a href="http://www.upei.ca/science/brian-wagner" target="_blank">Brian Wagner</a>, Department of Chemistry, UPEI&nbsp;</p>

		<p><a href="http://www.uhnres.utoronto.ca/facilities/LAB.htm" target="_blank">Robert Weersink</a>, University Health Network, University of Toronto</p>

		<p><a href="http://medbio.utoronto.ca/faculty/wilson.html" target="_blank">Brian Wilson</a>, Department of Medical Biophysics, University of Toronto</p>

		<p><a href="http://medbio.utoronto.ca/faculty/zheng.html" target="_blank">Gang Zheng</a>, Department of Medical Biophysics, University of Toronto</p>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>7</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>The Team</title>
		<p>The <strong>Biomedical Optics Research Group</strong> is led by Dr. William Whelan of the Department of Physics, University of Prince Edward Island.</p>

		<p><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BWhelan%20May%202015.JPG" style="float:right; height:280px; width:300px" /></p>

		<div><em>&ldquo;</em><em>The primary focus of my research is on the emerging area of optoacoustics. This non</em><em>-in</em><em>vasive, new area of research, allows for three-dimensional imaging of objects using lasers and integration o</em><em>f reflected sound waves. Currently, my research is focused on the development of emerging technolo</em><em>gies for the biomedical science sector including novel methods for disease detection and cancer management. Howev</em><em>er, the technology may find wider application in the material science and life science sectors. Specifically, we are investigating the potential of interstitial thermal therapy as an effective modality for the treatment of disease, including the thermal destruction of small solid tumors. We are currently focusing our efforts on the treatment of prostate cancer. However, the general goal of this work is to optimize and control interstitial thermal therapy for a variety of tissue pathologies.&rdquo;</em></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>Click below for more information:</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="http://www.upei.ca/science/william-m-whelan" target="_blank">William Whelan, Faculty of Science Web Page</a></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/william_whelan.pdf" target="_blank">William Whelan&#39;s Curriculum Vitae</a></div>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>12</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Funding Partners</title>
		<table align="center" border="0">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<p>&nbsp;</p>

						<p class="rteindent1"><a href="http://support.pcff.ca/site/PageServer?pagename=RFD_14_Home" target="_blank"><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/RFD_15th_Anniv_Logo_png.png" style="height:160px; width:200px" /></a></p>

						<p class="rteindent1"><a href="http://support.pcff.ca/site/PageServer?pagename=RFD_14_Home" target="_blank"><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/pcff.png" style="height:50px; width:200px" /></a></p>

						<p>&nbsp;</p>

						<p><a href="http://www.upei.ca/home/" target="_blank" title="http://www.upei.ca/home/"><img alt="UPEI" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/UPEI%20Logo.jpg" style="height:61px; width:314px" /></a></p>

						<p>&nbsp;</p>

						<p>&nbsp;<a href="http://www.acoa-apeca.gc.ca/English/Pages/Home.aspx" target="_blank" title="http://www.acoa-apeca.gc.ca/English/Pages/Home.aspx"><img alt="ACOA" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/ACOA%20Logo.jpg" style="height:75px; width:314px" /></a></p>
					</td>
					<td>
						<p class="rteindent2"><a href="http://www.chairs-chaires.gc.ca/home-accueil-eng.aspx" style="text-decoration: underline; color: rgb(255, 69, 0);" target="_blank"><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/CRC%20Logo.gif" style="height:22px; width:257px" /></a></p>

						<p class="rteindent1"><a href="http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/193.html" style="text-decoration: underline; color: rgb(255, 69, 0);" target="_blank" title="http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/193.html"><img alt="CIHR" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/CIHR%20Logo.jpg" style="height:196px; width:314px" /></a></p>

						<p class="rteindent3"><a href="http://www.innovation.ca/en/" style="text-decoration: underline; color: rgb(255, 69, 0);" target="_blank"><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/CFI%20Logo.gif" style="height:57px; width:200px" /></a></p>

						<p class="rteindent1"><a href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/index_eng.asp" target="_blank" title="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/index_eng.asp"><img alt="NSERC" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/NSERC%20Logo.jpg" style="height:139px; width:314px" /></a></p>
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>&nbsp;</td>
					<td>&nbsp;</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>

		<p class="rteindent4"><a href="http://www.cipi.ulaval.ca/" target="_blank"><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/CIPI%20Logo.jpg" style="height:100px; width:800px" /></a></p>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>13</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Project Titles by Funding Institution</title>
		<div><strong><a href="http://www.acoa-apeca.gc.ca/English/ImLookingFor/ProgramInformation/AtlanticInnovationFund/Pages/AtlanticInnovationFund.aspx">Atlantic Innovation Fund</a> (AIF), <a href="http://www.acoa-apeca.gc.ca/English/Pages/Home.aspx">Atlantic Canada Opportunies Agency </a>(ACOA)</strong></div>

		<ul>
			<li>Biophotonics platform for real-time assessment of cancer therapy effectiveness (2008-2013)</li>
		</ul>

		<div><strong><a href="http://www.cipi.ulaval.ca/">Canadian Institute for Photonic Innovations</a> (CIPI)</strong></div>

		<div><em>Principal Investigator: O. Levi, University of Toronto</em></div>

		<ul>
			<li>Development of integrated optical bio-sensors for continuous real-time monitoring of cancer&nbsp;and infection progression, and therapy efficacy in living subjects (2008-2011)</li>
		</ul>

		<div><strong><a href="http://www.chairs-chaires.gc.ca/home-accueil-eng.aspx">Canada Research Chair Program </a>(CRC)</strong></div>

		<ul>
			<li>UPEI Research Chair in Biomedical Optics (2008-2012)</li>
		</ul>

		<div><strong><a href="http://www.innovation.ca/en/">Canada Foundation for Innovation</a> (CFI) </strong></div>

		<ul>
			<li>Integrated optical platform for advancing biomedical physics (2008-2011)</li>
			<li>Advanced biomedical ultrasound imaging and spectroscopy laboratory: from 1 to 1000MHz (2007-2011)&nbsp;<em>-</em> <em>Principal Investigator: M. Kolios, Ryerson University</em> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
			<li>Facility for advanced bioacoustophotonics and biomolecular microfluidic photoacoustics (2007-2011)&nbsp;<em>- Principal Investigator: A. Mandelis, University of Toronto</em></li>
		</ul>

		<div><strong><a href="http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/193.html">Canadian Institutes of Health Research </a>(CIHR)</strong></div>

		<ul>
			<li>Integrated optical platform for real-time assessment of thermal therapy for prostate cancer (2007-2010)</li>
		</ul>

		<div><strong><a href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/index_eng.asp">National Sciences and Engineering Research Council</a>&nbsp;(NSERC)</strong></div>

		<ul>
			<li>An optical and optoacoustics platform for laser therapeutics (2011-2016)</li>
			<li>A multitasking optical delivery and guidance system for laser heating of biomaterials (2006-2011)</li>
			<li>Functional OptoAcoustic (fOA) imaging for monitoring and guiding cancer treatments (2006-2009)</li>
		</ul>

		<p><a href="http://support.pcff.ca/site/PageServer?pagename=RFD_14_Home">Prostate Cancer Fight Fund (PCFF) - Ride for Dad</a></p>

		<ul>
			<li>Using optoacoustic imaging to monitor laser thermal therapy of prostate cancer (2015-2016)</li>
		</ul>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>5</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Links</title>
		<p>Funding Partners:<a href="http://www.innovation.ca/en/navigator?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=logo&amp;utm_campaign=logo+navigator+promotion+EN" target="_blank"><img alt="CFI Research Facilities Navigator" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Navigator-button-EN_0.png" style="float:right; height:51px; width:168px" /></a></p>

		<ul>
			<li><a href="http://www.acoa-apeca.gc.ca/English/Pages/Home.aspx" target="_blank">Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency</a> (ACOA)</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.innovation.ca/en/" target="_blank">Canada Foundation for Innovation </a>(CFI)</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.chairs-chaires.gc.ca/home-accueil-eng.aspx" target="_blank">Canada Research Chairs</a> (CRC)</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.cipi.ulaval.ca/" target="_blank">Canadian Institute for Photonic Innovations</a> (CIPI)</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/193.html" target="_blank">Canadian Institutes of Health Research</a> (CIHR)</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/index_eng.asp" target="_blank">Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council </a>(NSERC)</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.upei.ca/home/" target="_blank">University of Prince Edward Island</a> (UPEI)</li>
		</ul>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>Press Releases and Media Coverage:</div>

		<ul>
			<li><a href="http://news.upei.ca/media/2015/06/03/telus-ride-dad-supports-prostate-cancer-research-upei-s-dr-bill-whelan">TELUS Ride for Dad supports prostate cancer research of UPEI&rsquo;s Dr. Bill Whelan</a> - UPEI Media Release, June 3, 2015</li>
			<li><a href="http://news.upei.ca/media/2014/08/19/sound-cancer-upei-researchers-confirm-cancerous-tissues-can-be-detected-their-uniqu" target="_blank">The sound of cancer: UPEI researchers confirm cancerous tissues can be detected by their unique &quot;pitch&quot;</a> - UPEI Media Release, August 19, 2014</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/prince-edward-island/cancer-explored-by-optoacoustics-without-surgery-1.2740328" target="_blank">Cancer explored by optoacoustics without surgery</a> - CBC Prince Edward Island, August 19, 2014</li>
			<li><a href="http://spie.org/x84919.xml" target="_blank">William Whelan works toward diagnostic technology for prostate cancer</a> - SPIE, January 6, 2012</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/technology/a-healing-light-how-lasers-can-diagnose-and-treat-disease/article4238487/" target="_blank">A healing light: how lasers can diagnose and treat disease</a> - The Globe and Mail, December 7, 2011</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/prince-edward-island/story/2011/11/30/pei-prostate-cancer-research-584.html" target="_blank">Research could allow doctors to hear tumours</a> - CBC Prince Edward Island, November 30, 2011</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KXNRVVR-gDs" target="_blank">The sound of cancer</a> - UPEI YouTube video, September 27, 2011</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.photonics.com/Article.aspx?PID=1&amp;VID=8&amp;IID=8&amp;AID=35036" target="_blank">Tracking cancer with light and sound</a> &ndash; Biophotonics, September, 2008</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.senomedical.com/index.php?Itemid=59&amp;id=787&amp;option=com_content&amp;task=view" target="_blank">Seno Medical Instruments Launches First-Ever Commercially Available Opto-Acoustic Small Animal Imaging Research System</a> &ndash; Seno, July 1, 2008</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.upei.ca/news/research-partnership-has-potential-benefit-human-and-animal-health" target="_blank">Research partnership has potential to benefit human and animal health</a> &ndash; UPEI Media Release, June 27, 2008</li>
			<li><a href="http://www.upei.ca/news/node/4181" target="_blank">UPEI research projects draw major investment from Atlantic Innovation Fund</a> &ndash; UPEI Media Release, January 21, 2008</li>
		</ul>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>17</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Point Radiance Spectroscopy</title>
		<p>There is a need for optical techniques to monitor tissues during and after therapies such as laser interstitial thermal therapy (LITT) and photodynamic therapy (PDT). LITT delivers energy to tissues in a form of light that is absorbed by chromophores and transformed into heat in a very selective and localized way. PDT also relies on localized light delivery. Both techniques require knowledge of spatially-resolved tissue optical properties that affect light propagation and energy deposition. Optical parameters of interest include absorption and scattering properties, chromophore identiﬁcation, and localization. A detection technique that could monitor changes in optical propagation in real time would be very beneﬁcial for online treatment. Aside from LITT and PDT, a noninvasive or minimally invasive optical modality could provide a convenient solution for routine medical diagnostics of organs and tissues by detecting changes in the optical properties (optical inhomogeneities) produced by certain diseases.</p>

		<p>Light is often detected in tissues through interstitial ﬁbers in open or closed catheters. A commonly used probe (known as a ﬂuence probe) has an isotropic diffused sphere attached to the end of the ﬁber that measures the integrated light collected over a 4&pi; solid angle. Typically, optical properties can be determined by ﬁtting the diffusion theory for light transport in tissue to relative ﬂuence measurements performed at known source detector separations. To overcome a problem of nonuniqueness in the optical property recovery, interstitial characterization of tissue optical properties has typically required absolute ﬂuence measurements that can be difﬁcult to obtain accurately.</p>

		<p>With the development of directional sensors, alternative characterization and monitoring techniques have emerged. Point radiance spectroscopy is an optical technique whereby light is collected within a small, well-defined angular cone thus providing information on angular light distribution at a selected point in turbid medium. Interestingly, the radiance-based light dosimetry was first applied to prostate interrogations. A later work from the same group was devoted to optimization of modeling algorithms for extracting global optical properties of phantoms from radiance measurements. Building on this we have demonstrated a potential for radiance based tissue coagulation detection and optical property determination; and more recently, radiance-based detection of localized gold nanoparticle inclusions inside Intralipid phantoms.</p>

		<p><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PRS%20Setup_0.jpg" style="height:384px; width:915px" /></p>

		<p><em>Source: Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer,</em><em>&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong></em><em>. Detection of localized inclusions of gold nanoparticles in Intralipid-1% by point-radiance spectroscopy, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 16(7), 077003. 2011.</em></p>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

		<p><em><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Radiance%20Measurements.jpg" style="height:442px; width:795px" /></em></p>

		<p><em>Source:&nbsp;</em><em>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, I. Alex Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Radiance detection of non-scattering inclusions in turbid media, Biomedical Optics Express, 2012 (in press).</em></p>

		<hr />
		<p><strong>Published articles:</strong></p>

		<div>
			<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan G Montgomery, Bo Pang, Yi Wang, Chao Zhang, Zhiyuan Li, Younan Xia and <strong>William M Whelan</strong>. &ldquo;Interstitial diffuse radiance spectroscopy of gold nanocages and nanorods in bulk muscle tissues&rdquo;, International Journal of Nanomedicine 10(2):1307-1320, 2015. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/IJN%20Grabtchak%202015.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

			<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan Montgomery, and&nbsp;<strong>William Whelan</strong>, Optical transport and spectroscopic properties of a canine prostate from ex vivo interstitial radiance measurements, Biomedical Optics, Miami, FL, April 2014.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BIOMED%20Grabtchak%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

			<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan G. Montgomery and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Feasibility of interstitial near-infrared radiance spectroscopy platform for ex vivo canine prostate studies: optical properties extraction, hemoglobin and water concentration and gold nanoparticles detection, Journal of Biomedical Optics 19(5):057003, 2014.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

			<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan G. Montgomery and&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Optical absorption and scattering properties of bulk porcine muscle phantoms from interstitial radiance measurements in 650-900 nm range, Phys. Med. Biol. 59:2431, 2014.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Grabtchak%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

			<p>Serge Grabtchak, Kristen B. Callaghan, and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Tagging photons with gold nanoparticles as localized absorbers in optical measurements in turbid media, Biomedical Optics Express 4(12):2989-3006, 2013.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BOE%20Grabtchak%202013.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

			<p>Serge Grabtchak, Elena Tonkopi and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optical detection of gold nanoparticles in a prostate-shaped porcine phantom, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 18(7):077005, 2013. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202013.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>
		</div>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, I. Alex Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Radiance detection of non-scattering inclusions in turbid media, Biomedical Optics Express, 3 (11), pp. 3001-3011, 2012.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BOE%20Grabtchak%202012b.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Separation of absorption and scattering properties of turbid media using relative spectrally resolved cw radiance measurements, Biomedical Optics Express, 3 (10), pp. 2371-2380, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BOE%20Grabtchak%202012a.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, Florian Foschum , Andre Liemert , Alwin Kienle and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Experimental spectro-angular mapping of light distribution in turbid media, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 17, 067007, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202012.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Spectro-angular mapping of localized gold inclusions in Intralipid phantoms, Proc. of SPIE Vol. 8427, 84271R, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Grabtchak%202012.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Radiance spectroscopy tool box for characterizing Au nanoparticles in tissue mimicking phantoms as applied to prostate, Journal of Cancer Science and Therapy, S1-008, 2011.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JCST%20Grabtchak%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Spatially-resolved probing of biological phantoms by point-radiance spectroscopy. Optical Fibers, Sensors, and Devices for Biomedical Diagnostics and Treatment XI, edited by Israel Gannot. Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7894, 78940A. 2011.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Grabtchak%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Detection of localized inclusions of gold nanoparticles in Intralipid-1% by point-radiance spectroscopy, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 16(7), 077003. 2011.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler&nbsp;J Palmer,&nbsp;and&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Point-radiance Spectroscopy for localized chromophore identification in biological phantoms. 11th OWLS - Optics Within Life Sciences, Quebec City, Quebec, September 29-30, 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/OWLS%20Grabtchak%20Poster%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee CL Chin, Brendan Lloyd,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and I. Alex Vitkin, Interstitial point radiance spectroscopy of turbid media, Journal of Applied Physics, 105, 102025, 2009 (Special Topic: Applied Biophysics), (Invited).&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JAP%20Chin%202009.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee Chin, Arthur Worthington,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and I. Alex Vitkin, Determination of the optical properties of turbid media using relative interstitial radiance measurements: Monte Carlo study, experimental verification and sensitivity analysis, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 12, 064027, 2007.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Chin%202007.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee Chin,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and I. Alex Vitkin, Perturbative diffusion theory formalism for interpreting temporal light intensity changes during laser interstitial thermal therapy, Physics in Medicine and Biology<em>,</em>&nbsp;52 (6), 1659-74, 2007.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Chin%202007.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee CL Chin,&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and I Alex Vitkin, Information content of point radiance measurements in turbid media:&nbsp;implications for interstitial optical property quantification, Applied Optics, 45(9), 2101-14, 2006.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Applied%20Optics%20Chin%202006.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee CL Chin, Brian C Wilson,&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and I Alex Vitkin, Radiance-based monitoring of the extent of tissue coagulation&nbsp;during laser interstitial thermal therapy, Optics Letters, 29(9), 959-961, 2004.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Optics%20Letters%20Chin%202004.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee C.L. Chin,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and I. Alex Vitkin, Models and measurements of light intensity changes during laser interstitial thermal therapy: implications for optical monitoring of the coagulation boundary location, Physics in Medicine and Biology, 48, 543-559, 2003.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Chin%202003.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Lee Chin, Mihaela Pop,&nbsp;<strong>William Whelan</strong>, Michael Sherar and Alex Vitkin, Optical method using fluence or radiance measurements to monitor thermal therapy, Review of&nbsp;Scientific Instruments, 74(1), 393-395, 2003.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Rev%20Sci%20Instr%20Chin%202003.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>14</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Scientific Library</title>
		<p><strong>See&nbsp;</strong><a href="http://www.researchgate.net/profile/William_Whelan2" target="_blank">William M Whelan</a> on <a href="http://www.researchgate.net/" target="_blank">ResearchGate</a>.</p>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

		<p><em><strong>Selected Publications<img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/j0439532.jpg" style="float:right; height:300px; width:450px" /></strong></em></p>

		<p><strong>2015</strong></p>

		<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan G Montgomery, Bo Pang, Yi Wang, Chao Zhang, Zhiyuan Li, Younan Xia and <strong>William M Whelan</strong>. &ldquo;Interstitial diffuse radiance spectroscopy of gold nanocages and nanorods in bulk muscle tissues&rdquo;, International Journal of Nanomedicine 10(2):1307-1320, 2015. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/IJN%20Grabtchak%202015.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<div>
			<div><strong>2014</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>
				<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan Montgomery, and <strong>William Whelan</strong>, Optical transport and spectroscopic properties of a canine prostate from ex vivo interstitial radiance measurements, Biomedical Optics, Miami, FL, April 2014. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BIOMED%20Grabtchak%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

				<p>Michelle Patterson, Christopher B. Riley, Michael C. Kolios, and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic characterization of prostate cancer in an in vivo transgenic murine model, Journal of Biomedical Optics 19(5):056008, 2014. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Patterson%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

				<p>Michelle Patterson, Jonathan Horrocks, Bruno Ouimet, Sophie St. Hilaire and <strong>William Whelan</strong>, Optoacoustic detection of Kudoa thyrsites infection in Atlantic Salmon, SPIE BiOS, San Francisco, CA, February 2014. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIEPoster2014Whelan_155pm.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

				<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan G. Montgomery and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Feasibility of interstitial near-infrared radiance spectroscopy platform for ex vivo canine prostate studies: optical properties extraction, hemoglobin and water concentration and gold nanoparticles detection, Journal of Biomedical Optics 19(5):057003, 2014. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

				<p>Serge Grabtchak, Logan G. Montgomery and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Optical absorption and scattering properties of bulk porcine muscle phantoms from interstitial radiance measurements in 650-900 nm range, Phys. Med. Biol. 59:2431, 2014. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Grabtchak%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

				<p><strong>2013</strong></p>

				<p>Serge Grabtchak, Kristen B. Callaghan, and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Tagging photons with gold nanoparticles as localized absorbers in optical measurements in turbid media, Biomedical Optics Express 4(12):2989-3006, 2013. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BOE%20Grabtchak%202013.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

				<p>Serge Grabtchak, Elena Tonkopi and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optical detection of gold nanoparticles in a prostate-shaped porcine phantom, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 18(7):077005, 2013.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202013.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>
			</div>

			<div>Shiv veer Singh, Rabin Bissessur and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Characterization and stability of gold nanocages for use as contrast agents in optoacoustics. Canadian Association of Physicists Congress, Montreal, Quebec, May 2013. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/CAP%20Singh%202013.pdf">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>2012</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, I. Alex Vitkin and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Radiance detection of non-scattering inclusions in turbid media, Biomedical Optics Express, 3 (11), pp. 3001-3011, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BOE%20Grabtchak%202012b.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Separation of absorption and scattering properties of turbid media using relative spectrally resolved cw radiance measurements, Biomedical Optics Express, 3 (10), pp. 2371-2380, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/BOE%20Grabtchak%202012a.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, Florian Foschum , Andre Liemert , Alwin Kienle and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Experimental spectro-angular mapping of light distribution in turbid media, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 17, 067007, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202012.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Spectro-angular mapping of localized gold inclusions in Intralipid phantoms, Proc. of SPIE Vol. 8427, 84271R, 2012. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Grabtchak%202012.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Annie Lad&eacute;route; Michelle P. Patterson; Michael C. Kolios; <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Frequency analysis of optoacoustic signals in laser heated tissues, Proc. of SPIE Vol. 8223, 822341, 2012.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Lad%C3%A9route%202012.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>2011</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Michelle P. Patterson, Christopher B. Riley, Michael C. Kolios and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optoacoustic signal amplitude and frequency spectrum analysis laser heated bovine liver ex vivo, IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium Proceedings pp. 300-303, 2011.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/IEEE%20Patterson%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Radiance spectroscopy tool box for characterizing Au nanoparticles in tissue mimicking phantoms as applied to prostate, Journal of Cancer Science and Therapy, S1-008, 2011. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JCST%20Grabtchak%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>L.C.L Chin, W.M. Whelan and I.A. Vitkin, Optical fiber sensors in biomedical applications, Optical-Thermal Response of Laser Irradiated Tissue: 2nd edition, A.J. Welch and M.J.C. van Gemert, editors (Plenum, New York), chapter 17, April 2011.&nbsp;<a href="http://www.springer.com/physics/book/978-90-481-8830-7" target="_blank">abstract</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Behrouz Soroushian, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Michael C. Kolios. Dynamics of laser induced thermoelastic expansion of native and coagulated ex-vivo soft tissue samples and their optical and thermo-mechanical properties. Photons Plus Ultrasound: Imaging and Sensing 2011, edited by Alexander A. Oraevsky, Lihong V. Wang. Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7899, 78990Z. 2011. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Soroushian%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Spatially-resolved probing of biological phantoms by point-radiance spectroscopy. Optical Fibers, Sensors, and Devices for Biomedical Diagnostics and Treatment XI, edited by Israel Gannot. Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7894, 78940A. 2011. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Grabtchak%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler J. Palmer, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Detection of localized inclusions of gold nanoparticles in Intralipid-1% by point-radiance spectroscopy, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 16(7), 077003. 2011. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Grabtchak%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a><br />
				&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>2010</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Behrouz Soroushian, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and Michael C. Kolios. Study of laser induced thermoelastic deformation of native and coagulated ex vivo bovine liver tissues for estimating their optical and thermo mechanical properties, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 15(6), 065002. 2010. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Soroushian%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a><br />
				&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Matthew Rodrigues, Robert A. Weersink, and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Assessment of thermal coagulation in ex vivo tissues using Raman spectroscopy, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 15. 15(6), 068001. 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21198214" target="_blank">abstract</a><br />
				&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Serge Grabtchak, Tyler&nbsp;J Palmer,&nbsp;and <strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Point-radiance Spectroscopy for localized chromophore identification in biological phantoms. 11th OWLS - Optics Within Life Sciences, Quebec City, Quebec, September 29-30, 2010. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/OWLS%20Grabtchak%20Poster%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Tyler J Palmer and <strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic detection and imaging of thermally damaged ex vivo tissues. 11th OWLS - Optics Within Life Sciences, Quebec City, Quebec, September 29-30, 2010. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/OWLS%20Palmer%20Poster%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>
		</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>Michelle P Patterson, Chris B Riley, Michael C Kolios and <strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic imaging in a murine prostate cancer model. Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia National Conference, Broadbeach, Australia, August 2010. (Best Poster Award: 1 of 5). <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PCFA%20Patterson%20Australia%20Poster%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>Behrouz Soroushian, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Michael C. Kolios. Dynamics of thermoeleastic expansion for native and coagulated ex-vivo bovine liver tissues. Photons Plus Ultrasound: Imaging and Sensing 2010, edited by Alexander A. Oraevsky, Lihong V. Wang. Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7564, 75641N, 2010. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Soroushian%20%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>Michelle P. Patterson, Michel G. Arsenault, Chris Riley, Michael Kolios and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic imaging of an animal model of prostate cancer. Photons Plus Ultrasound 2010, edited by Alexander A. Oraevsky, Lihong V. Wang, Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7564, 75641B, 2010. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Patterson%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><strong>2009</strong></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><strong>W Whelan</strong>, M Arsenault, M MacPhee, and M Kolios. Optoacoustic detection of tissue thermal damage. Medical Physics, 4306-4307, 2009. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Medical%20Physics%20Whelan%202009.pdf" target="_blank">abstract</a></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>Lee CL Chin, Brendan Lloyd, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and I. Alex Vitkin, Interstitial point radiance spectroscopy of turbid media, Journal of Applied Physics, 105, 102025, 2009 (Special Topic: Applied Biophysics), (Invited). <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JAP%20Chin%202009.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>
			<div>Michel G. Arsenault, Michael C. Kolios and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optoacoustic detection of thermal lesions, Proc. SPIE, Vol 7177, 71771V, 2009. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Arsenault%202009.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Behrouz Soroushian, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and Michael C. Kolios, Assessment of opto-mechanical behavior of biological samples by interferometry, Proc. SPIE, Vol 7177, 71771X, 2009. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Soroushian%202009.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a><a href="http://web.physics.ryerson.ca/mkolios/publications/sorouhsian_SPIE09.pdf">&nbsp;</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>2008</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Gloria M. Spirou, Andreas Mandelis, I. Alex Vitkin and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Frequency domain photothermoacoustic signal amplitude dependence on the optical properties of&nbsp;water: turbid polyvinyl chloride-plastisol (PVCP) system, Applied Optics<em>, </em>Vol. 47, Issue 14, pp. 2564-2573, 2008. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Applied%20Optics%20Spirou%202008.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>GM Spirou, A Mandelis, IA Vitkin and <strong>WM Whelan</strong>, A calibration technique for frequency domain photothermoacoustics, European Physical Journal (Special Topics<em>), </em>153, 491-494, 2008<em>. </em><a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Eur%20Phys%20J%20Spirou%202008.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>
				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div>M. Rodrigues, R. Weersink, and <strong>W. Whelan</strong>, Raman spectroscopy: Potential for detecting tissue coagulation during laser therapy, in Biomedical Optics, OSA Technical Digest, Optical Society of America, paper BTuF46, 2008. <a href="http://www.opticsinfobase.org/abstract.cfm?URI=BIOMED-2008-BTuF46" target="_blank">abstract</a></div>

				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div>Robin F. Castelino, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong> and Michael C. Kolios, Photoacoustic detection of protein coagulation in albumen-based phantoms, Proc. SPIE Vol 6856, 685626, 2008. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Castelino%202008.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div><strong>2007</strong></div>

				<div>&nbsp;&nbsp;</div>
			</div>

			<div>Lee Chin, Arthur Worthington, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and I. Alex Vitkin, Determination of the optical properties of turbid media using relative interstitial radiance measurements: Monte Carlo study, experimental verification and sensitivity analysis, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 12, 064027, 2007. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Chin%202007.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Lee Chin, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and I. Alex Vitkin, Perturbative diffusion theory formalism for interpreting temporal light intensity changes during laser interstitial thermal therapy, Physics in Medicine and Biology<em>, </em>52 (6), 1659-74, 2007. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Chin%202007.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>2006</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Lee CL Chin, <strong>William M Whelan</strong> and I Alex Vitkin, Information content of point radiance measurements in turbid media:&nbsp;implications for interstitial optical property quantification, Applied Optics, 45(9), 2101-14, 2006. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Applied%20Optics%20Chin%202006.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>
				<div>Madhu Jain, Carl Kumaradas, Farrokh Sharifi and <strong>William Whelan</strong>, Uncertainty and sensitivity analysis for a laser-irradiation tissue model, IEEE Proceedings, Electrical and Computer Engineering, 1171-1175, 2006. <a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/freeabs_all.jsp?arnumber=4055003" target="_blank">abstract</a></div>

				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div>Christian Richter, Gloria Spirou, Alexander A. Oraevsky, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong> and Michael Kolios, Examination of contrast mechanisms in optoacoustic imaging of thermal lesions, Proc. SPIE, Vol 6086, 60861K, 2006.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Richter%202006.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div><strong>2005</strong></div>

				<div>&nbsp;&nbsp;</div>
			</div>

			<div>Ying Fan, Andreas Mandelis, Gloria Spirou, I. Alex Vitkin and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Laser photothermoacoustic heterodyned lock-in depth profilometry in turbid tissue phantoms, Physical Review E, 72, 051908, 1- 11, 2005.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Phys%20Review%20Fan%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Gloria M. Spirou, Alexander A. Oraevsky, I. Alex Vitkin and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optical and acoustic properties at 1064nm of polyvinyl chloride-plastisol (PCP) for use as a tissue phantom in biomedical optoacoustics, Physics in Medicine and Biology, 50, N141-N153, 2005. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Spirou%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Sean R H Davidson, I. Alex Vitkin, Michael D. Sherar and <strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Characterization of measurement artefacts in fluoroptic temperature sensors: Implications for laser thermal therapy at 810 nm, Lasers in Surgery and Medicine, 36, 297-306 2005. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/LSM%20Davidson%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Lee C.L. Chin, Sean R. Davidson and I. Alex Vitkin, A novel strategy for monitoring laser thermal therapy based on changes in optothermal properties of heated tissues, International Journal of Thermophysics , 26, 233-241, 2005. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/IJT%20Whelan%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div><strong>2004</strong></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Lee CL Chin, Brian C Wilson, <strong>William M Whelan</strong> and I Alex Vitkin, Radiance-based monitoring of the extent of tissue coagulation&nbsp;during laser interstitial thermal therapy, Optics Letters, 29(9), 959-961, 2004. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Optics%20Letters%20Chin%202004.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>
				<div>Y. Fan, A. Mandelis, G. Spirou, A. I. Vitkin and <strong>W. M. Whelan</strong>, Three-dimensional photothermoacoustic depth-profilometric imaging by use of linear frequency sweep heterodyne method, Proc. SPIE , Vol. 5320, p. 113-127, 2004. (Invited). <a href="http://proceedings.spiedigitallibrary.org/proceeding.aspx?articleid=839006" target="_blank">abstract</a></div>

				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div>G.M. Spirou, I.A. Vitkin, B.C. Wilson, <strong>W.M. Whelan</strong>, P.M. Henrichs, K. Mehta, T. Miller, A. Yee, J. Meador and A.A. Oraevsky, Development and testing of an optoacoustic imaging system for monitoring and guiding prostate cancer therapies, Proc. SPIE,&nbsp;Vol. 5320,&nbsp;44-56, 2004. &nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Spirou%202004.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

				<div>&nbsp;</div>

				<div><strong>2003</strong></div>

				<div>&nbsp;&nbsp;</div>
			</div>

			<div>Lee C.L. Chin, <strong>William M. Whelan</strong> and I. Alex Vitkin, Models and measurements of light intensity changes during laser interstitial thermal therapy: implications for optical monitoring of the coagulation boundary location, Physics in Medicine and Biology, 48, 543-559, 2003. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Chin%202003.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>

			<div>&nbsp;</div>

			<div>Lee Chin, Mihaela Pop, <strong>William Whelan</strong>, Michael Sherar and Alex Vitkin, Optical method using fluence or radiance measurements to monitor thermal therapy, Review of&nbsp;Scientific Instruments, 74(1), 393-395, 2003. <a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Rev%20Sci%20Instr%20Chin%202003.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></div>
		</div>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>11</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Students and Research Personnel</title>
		<p><em><strong>Current:</strong></em></p>

		<ul>
			<li><strong>Serge Grabtchak</strong>, Research Associate, UPEI</li>
			<li><strong>Shiv Veer Singh Chauhan</strong>, Graduate Student (MSc), UPEI (Chemistry) - Gold nanocages as optical contrast agents for optical and optoacoustic imaging</li>
		</ul>

		<p><em><strong>Alumni:</strong></em></p>

		<ul>
			<li><strong>Michelle Patterson</strong>, Graduate Student (PhD), UPEI (Biomedical Sciences) - Evaluation of optoacoustic frequency analysis sensitivity to discriminate healthy and neoplastic tissues and to monitor treatment-induced physiological&nbsp;changes</li>
			<li><strong>Franklin Che</strong>, Graduate Student (PhD), Dalhousie University (Electrical and Computer Engineering) - Investigation of surface plasmonic resonance of material&nbsp;surfaces for biomedical applications</li>
			<li><strong>Annie Laderoute</strong>&nbsp;(MSc)&nbsp;- <a href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/obj/thesescanada/vol2/002/MR94072.pdf" target="_blank">Amplitude and frequency content analysis of optoacoustic signals in laser heated ex-vivo tissues</a></li>
			<li><strong>Evan Owen</strong>&nbsp;(MSc) - <a href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/obj/thesescanada/vol2/002/MR94050.pdf" target="_blank">Investigations of a fluorescence based method for early detecti<strong><strong><strong><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/j0439409.jpg" style="float:right; font-weight:normal; height:220px; width:300px" /></strong></strong></strong>on of mastitis in dairy cows</a></li>
			<li><strong>Radek Sadowski</strong>&nbsp;(MSc) - <a href="http://digitalcommons.ryerson.ca/islandora/object/RULA%3A1171" target="_blank">Measuring the effects of temperature on optical propagation in heated tissues using Point Radiance Spectroscopy</a></li>
			<li><strong>Hisham Assi </strong>(MSc) - <a href="http://digitalcommons.ryerson.ca/islandora/object/RULA%3A1050" target="_blank">A new CEM43 thermal dose model based on Vogel-Tammann-Fulcher kinetics</a></li>
			<li><strong>Brendan Lloyd </strong>(MSc) - <a href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/obj/thesescanada/vol2/002/MR52689.PDF" target="_blank">Characterization of non-homogeneous turbid media with spectroscopic radiance measurements from a single location</a></li>
			<li><strong>Lee Chin</strong> (PhD) - <a href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/obj/thesescanada/vol2/002/NR39543.PDF" target="_blank">Optical diagnostics toolbox for laser&nbsp;interstitial thermal therapy</a></li>
			<li><strong>Matthew Rodrigues</strong> (MSc) - <a href="http://digitalcommons.ryerson.ca/islandora/object/RULA%3A1063" target="_blank">The potential of Raman spectroscopy as a monitoring tool for thermal therapy</a></li>
			<li><strong>Robin Castelino</strong> (MASc) - <a href="http://digitalcommons.ryerson.ca/islandora/object/RULA%3A887" target="_blank">Biomedical applications of photoacoustics for thermal therapy</a></li>
			<li><strong>Madhu Jain </strong>(MASc) - <a href="http://digitalcommons.ryerson.ca/islandora/object/RULA%3A972" target="_blank">A thermal dose controller for laser interstitial thermal therapy</a></li>
			<li><strong>Gloria Spirou</strong> (MSc) -&nbsp; <a href="http://collectionscanada.gc.ca/ourl/res.php?url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;url_tim=2012-11-08T15%3A27%3A50Z&amp;url_ctx_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Actx&amp;rft_dat=32472888&amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fcollectionscanada.gc.ca%3Aamicus&amp;lang=eng" target="_blank">An investigation of pulsed and frequency&nbsp;domain photoacoustics and their&nbsp;applicability to biomedical studies</a></li>
			<li><strong>Mark Jarvi </strong>(MSc) - <a href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/obj/thesescanada/vol2/002/mr02515.pdf" target="_blank">In vitro and in vivo investigations of&nbsp;mild hyperthermic modulation of&nbsp;palladium-bacteriopheophorbide&nbsp;(WST09)-mediated photodynamic therapy&nbsp;doses</a></li>
			<li><strong>Vanessa Choy</strong> (MSc) - <a href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/obj/s4/f2/dsk4/etd/MQ84389.PDF" target="_blank">Real-time online fuzzy logic controller&nbsp;for laser interstitial thermal therapy</a></li>
		</ul>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>16</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Optoacoustic Imaging</title>
		<p>Laser Thermal Therapy (LTT) is a minimally invasive technique of destroying diseased tissue.&nbsp; The feasibility of LTT has been demonstrated in a number of sites including breast, brain, liver and prostate.&nbsp; Thermal therapy involves heating tissue to between 55 and 90 oC for several minutes resulting in cell death.&nbsp; Cell death occurs when thermal damage results in irreversible denaturation of proteins (i.e. coagulation), typically at temperatures above 55oC.&nbsp; Unlike hyperthermia (heating tissue to between 41-45 oC), thermal therapy acts as a stand-alone therapy and does not require further treatment from any additional techniques.</p>

		<p>Heating tissues result in highly variable outcomes which can result in insufficient treatment (leading to recurrence) or overly aggressive treatment. &nbsp;This necessitates precise and continuous monitoring during treatment.&nbsp; Real-time monitoring would ensure that the entire tumour has been destroyed while periprostatic critical structures are spared.&nbsp; The efficacy of LTT would be improved if treatment response during treatment could be measured. &nbsp;</p>

		<p>Currently, tissue temperatures are commonly being measured during LTT using point sensors (e.g. thermocouples, fluoroptic probes) which provide temperature information at specific locations.&nbsp; Monitoring using point sensors has proven to be inadequate due to the time delay in the conduction of thermal energy from the heating source to the temperature probe.&nbsp; This can result in temperatures exceeding safe limits close to the heating source before they are detected by the temperature probes resulting in undesirable tissue charring.</p>

		<p>Tissue temperature can also be monitored using MRI thermometry which provides three-dimensional maps of tissue temperature in real-time.&nbsp; However, this type of monitoring is commonly cost-prohibitive for most treatment centers. &nbsp;</p>

		<p>Optoacoustic (OA) imaging has the potential to provide three-dimensional information in real-time that may offer a means of monitoring the degree of thermal damage to the tissue during LTT.&nbsp; OA imaging takes advantage of the significant changes in tissue optical properties due to thermal coagulation.&nbsp; OA signals are strongly affected by the optical absorption and scattering coefficients, and mechanical properties of the target making coagulation an ideal target for OA imaging.</p>

		<p><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Optoacoustic%20Setup.jpg" style="height:429px; width:722px" /></p>

		<p><em>Source: Michelle P. Patterson, Christopher B. Riley, Michael C. Kolios and William M. Whelan, Optoacoustic signal amplitude and frequency spectrum analysis laser heated bovine liver ex vivo, IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium Proceedings pp. 300-303, 2011.</em></p>

		<p>&nbsp;</p>

		<p><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Optoacoustic%20Images.jpg" style="height:524px; width:633px" /></p>

		<p><em>Source: Michelle P Patterson, Chris B Riley, Michael C Kolios and</em><em>&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong></em><em>. Optoacoustic imaging in a murine prostate cancer model. Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia National Conference, Broadbeach, Australia, August 2010. (Best Poster Award: 1 of 5).</em></p>

		<hr />
		<p><strong>Published articles:</strong></p>

		<p>Michelle Patterson, Christopher B. Riley, Michael C. Kolios, and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic characterization of prostate cancer in an in vivo transgenic murine model, Journal of Biomedical Optics 19(5):056008, 2014.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Patterson%202014.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Shiv veer Singh, Rabin Bissessur and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Characterization and stability of gold nanocages for use as contrast agents in optoacoustics. Canadian Association of Physicists Congress, Montreal, Quebec, May 2013.&nbsp;<a href="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/CAP%20Singh%202013.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Annie Lad&eacute;route; Michelle P. Patterson; Michael C. Kolios;&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Frequency analysis of&nbsp; optoacoustic signals in laser heated tissues, Proc. of SPIE Vol. 8223, 822341, 2012.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Lad%C3%A9route%202012.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Michelle P. Patterson, Christopher B. Riley, Michael C. Kolios and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optoacoustic signal amplitude and frequency spectrum analysis laser heated bovine liver ex vivo, IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium Proceedings pp. 300-303, 2011.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/IEEE%20Patterson%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Behrouz Soroushian,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Michael C. Kolios. Dynamics of laser induced thermoelastic expansion of native and coagulated ex-vivo soft tissue samples and their optical and thermo-mechanical properties. Photons Plus Ultrasound: Imaging and Sensing 2011, edited by Alexander A. Oraevsky, Lihong V. Wang. Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7899, 78990Z. 2011.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Soroushian%202011.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Behrouz Soroushian,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, and Michael C. Kolios. Study of laser induced thermoelastic deformation of native and coagulated ex vivo bovine liver tissues for estimating their optical and thermo mechanical properties, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 15(6), 065002. 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/JBO%20Soroushian%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Tyler J Palmer and&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic detection and imaging of thermally damaged ex vivo tissues. 11th OWLS - Optics Within Life Sciences, Quebec City, Quebec, September 29-30, 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/OWLS%20Palmer%20Poster%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Michelle P Patterson, Chris B Riley, Michael C Kolios and&nbsp;<strong>William M Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic imaging in a murine prostate cancer model. Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia National Conference, Broadbeach, Australia, August 2010. (Best Poster Award: 1 of 5).&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PCFA%20Patterson%20Australia%20Poster%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Behrouz Soroushian,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Michael C. Kolios. Dynamics of thermoeleastic expansion for native and coagulated ex-vivo bovine liver tissues. Photons Plus Ultrasound: Imaging and Sensing 2010, edited by Alexander A. Oraevsky, Lihong V. Wang. Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7564, 75641N, 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Soroushian%20%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Michelle P. Patterson, Michel G. Arsenault, Chris Riley, Michael Kolios and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Optoacoustic imaging of an animal model of prostate cancer. Photons Plus Ultrasound 2010, edited by Alexander A. Oraevsky, Lihong V. Wang, Proc. of SPIE Vol. 7564, 75641B, 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Patterson%202010.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p><strong>W Whelan</strong>, M Arsenault, M MacPhee, and M Kolios. Optoacoustic detection of tissue thermal damage. Medical Physics, 4306-4307, 2009.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Medical%20Physics%20Whelan%202009.pdf" target="_blank">abstract</a></p>

		<p>Michel G. Arsenault, Michael C. Kolios and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optoacoustic detection of thermal lesions, Proc. SPIE, Vol 7177, 71771V, 2009.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Arsenault%202009.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Behrouz Soroushian,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and Michael C. Kolios, Assessment of opto-mechanical behavior of biological samples by interferometry, Proc. SPIE, Vol 7177, 71771X, 2009.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Soroushian%202009.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Gloria M. Spirou, Andreas Mandelis, I. Alex Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Frequency domain photothermoacoustic signal amplitude dependence on the optical properties of&nbsp;water: turbid polyvinyl chloride-plastisol (PVCP) system, Applied Optics<em>,</em>&nbsp;Vol. 47, Issue 14, pp. 2564-2573, 2008.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Applied%20Optics%20Spirou%202008.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>GM Spirou, A Mandelis, IA Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>WM Whelan</strong>, A calibration technique for frequency domain photothermoacoustics, European Physical Journal (Special Topics<em>),</em>&nbsp;153, 491-494, 2008<em>.</em>&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Eur%20Phys%20J%20Spirou%202008.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Robin F. Castelino,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and Michael C. Kolios, Photoacoustic detection of protein coagulation in albumen-based phantoms, Proc. SPIE Vol 6856, 685626, 2008.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Castelino%202008.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Madhu Jain, Carl Kumaradas, Farrokh Sharifi and&nbsp;<strong>William Whelan</strong>, Uncertainty and sensitivity analysis for a laser-irradiation tissue model, IEEE Proceedings, Electrical and Computer Engineering, 1171-1175, 2006.&nbsp;<a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/freeabs_all.jsp?arnumber=4055003" target="_blank">abstract</a></p>

		<p>Christian Richter, Gloria Spirou, Alexander A. Oraevsky,&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>&nbsp;and Michael Kolios, Examination of contrast mechanisms in optoacoustic imaging of thermal lesions, Proc. SPIE, Vol 6086, 60861K, 2006.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Richter%202006.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Ying Fan, Andreas Mandelis, Gloria Spirou, I. Alex Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Laser photothermoacoustic heterodyned lock-in depth profilometry in turbid tissue phantoms, Physical Review E, 72, 051908, 1- 11, 2005.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Phys%20Review%20Fan%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Gloria M. Spirou, Alexander A. Oraevsky, I. Alex Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Optical and acoustic properties at 1064nm of polyvinyl chloride-plastisol (PCP) for use as a tissue phantom in biomedical optoacoustics, Physics in Medicine and Biology, 50, N141-N153, 2005.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/PMB%20Spirou%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Sean R H Davidson, I. Alex Vitkin, Michael D. Sherar and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Characterization of measurement artefacts in fluoroptic temperature sensors: Implications for laser thermal therapy at 810 nm, Lasers in Surgery and Medicine, 36, 297-306 2005.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/LSM%20Davidson%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p><strong>William M. Whelan</strong>, Lee C.L. Chin, Sean R. Davidson and I. Alex Vitkin, A novel strategy for monitoring laser thermal therapy based on changes in optothermal properties of heated tissues, International Journal of Thermophysics , 26, 233-241, 2005.&nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/IJT%20Whelan%202005.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

		<p>Y. Fan, A. Mandelis, G. Spirou, A. I. Vitkin and&nbsp;<strong>W. M. Whelan</strong>, Three-dimensional photothermoacoustic depth-profilometric imaging by use of linear frequency sweep heterodyne method, Proc. SPIE , Vol. 5320, p. 113-127, 2004. (Invited).&nbsp;<a href="http://proceedings.spiedigitallibrary.org/proceeding.aspx?articleid=839006" target="_blank">abstract</a></p>

		<p>G.M. Spirou, I.A. Vitkin, B.C. Wilson,&nbsp;<strong>W.M. Whelan</strong>, P.M. Henrichs, K. Mehta, T. Miller, A. Yee, J. Meador and A.A. Oraevsky, Development and testing of an optoacoustic imaging system for monitoring and guiding prostate cancer therapies, Proc. SPIE,&nbsp;Vol. 5320,&nbsp;44-56, 2004. &nbsp;<a href="http://discoveryspace.upei.ca/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/SPIE%20Spirou%202004.pdf" target="_blank">pdf</a></p>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>4</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Contact Us</title>
		<div>For more information on the <strong>Biomedical Optics Research Group</strong>, contact:</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div><img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/whelan_0.jpg" style="float:right; height:281px; width:500px" /></div>

		<div>William M. Whelan</div>

		<div>Professor</div>

		<div>Department of Physics</div>

		<div>University of Prince Edward Island</div>

		<div>Charlottetown, PEI</div>

		<div>C1A 4P3</div>

		<div>Phone:&nbsp;1 902-566-0419</div>

		<div>Fax:&nbsp;1 902-566-0483</div>

		<div>Link:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:wwhelan@upei.ca">wwhelan@upei.ca</a></div>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>9</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>About Us</title>
		<p><img alt="Duffy Science Centre, UPEI" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Duffy%20Science%20Centre.jpg" style="float:right; height:300px; width:400px" />The <strong>Biomedical Optics Project</strong> combines groundbreaking research in two emerging areas of medical technology &ndash; optoacoustic imaging and laser thermal therapy &ndash; to develop new prostate cancer treatment technologies which can be precisely targeted to destroy tumours without harming adjacent tissues. The emerging multi-disciplinary field of biomedical optics uses light and other forms of radiant energy to image, analyze and manipulate living tissue at cellular and molecular levels, in a non-invasive or minimally invasive manner. The enormous potential of this technology to promote human and animal health is being pursued by a rapidly growing industry, focused on translating scientific discoveries around lasers, light and imaging into useful medical tools.</p>

		<div>The project links the <a href="http://www.upei.ca/home/" target="_blank">University of Prince Edward Island</a> (UPEI) <a href="http://www.upei.ca/physics/" target="_blank">Department of Physics </a>and the <a href="http://www.upei.ca/avc/" target="_blank">Atlantic Veterinary College </a>(AVC) with <a href="http://www.senomedical.com/" target="_blank">Seno Medical Instruments</a> of San Antonio Texas, <a href="http://www.uhn.ca/" target="_blank">Princess Margaret Hospital </a>and <a href="http://www.ryerson.ca/home.html" target="_blank">Ryerson University</a> of Toronto into a dynamic partnership. The target deliverables at project completion are prototype devices, instruments, and data demonstrating proof of principle of the application of fibre-optic based tissue characterization and Seno&rsquo;s globally patented optoacoustic diagnostic imaging technology to monitoring of thermal cancer therapy. The research may result in the integration of these two leading-edge technologies into a groundbreaking new cancer treatment modality, with potential for further applications to small animal research, ischemic stroke, and development of nutraceuticals and pharmaceuticals.</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

		<div>&nbsp;</div>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>15</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Raman Spectroscopy</title>
		<p>On a molecular scale, recent advances in Raman spectroscopy have been substantial, especially given the developments in CCD and photomultiplier (PMT) detection technologies. Raman spectroscopy probes the vibrational energy levels of molecules via inelastic optical scattering. Signals are much weaker than autofluorescence and hence high efficiency detection systems are required.</p>
		<div>
			Raman peaks are sensitive to tissue molecules and thus this method represents a powerful tool for tissue diagnosis, including optical biopsy applications. Choice of excitation wavelength depends on the application. Near-infrared excitation provides for the needed maximal penetration in tissues. However, determining the optimal wavelength is a trade-off between minimizing background autoflourescence (at higher NIR wavelength, i.e. 1064 nm) and maximizing Raman signal (at lower NIR 47 wavelength, i.e. 785 nm). Furthermore, the sensitivity of available detectors above 1 &micro;m is limited. As a result, 785 nm appears to be a good choice.&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			Raman spectra of thermally damaged tissues will be studied. It is anticipated that the Raman shift in collagen rich tissues, such as muscle, would be sensitive to the conformational changes in tissue proteins that occur during the coagulation process. Although there are limited published data that demonstrate the effects of temperature on Raman spectra of collagen in vitro, there appear to be no such studies in tissues.&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			Investigations in a number of ex vivo tissues including muscle, liver, kidney and prostate will be initiated to identify relevant Raman peaks and refine the technique before in vivo experimentation in rodent liver and canine prostate models. Novel Raman detection probes will be designed and fabricated, first for surface measurements, and then for interstitial applications. This new application of Raman spectroscopy will advance our understanding of the structural, compositional and molecular characteristics of normal and diseased tissues (i.e. optical biopsy) and how detected changes can enable novel approaches for guiding laser therapies.</div>
		<div>
			&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			<img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Raman.jpeg" style="width: 690px; height: 400px;" />&nbsp;&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			<img alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Raman%202.jpeg" style="width: 700px; height: 521px;" /></div>
		<div>
			&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			<em>Source:&nbsp;Matthew Rodrigues, Robert A. Weersink, and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Assessment of thermal coagulation in ex vivo tissues using Raman spectroscopy, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 15. 15(6), 068001. 2010.</em></div>
		<div>
			&nbsp;</div>
		<div>
			<hr />
			<p><strong>Published articles:</strong></p>
		</div>
		<p>Matthew Rodrigues, Robert A. Weersink, and&nbsp;<strong>William M. Whelan</strong>. Assessment of thermal coagulation in ex vivo tissues using Raman spectroscopy, Journal of Biomedical Optics, 15. 15(6), 068001. 2010.&nbsp;<a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21198214" target="_blank"><strong>abstract</strong></a></p>
		<p>M. Rodrigues, R. Weersink, and&nbsp;<strong>W. Whelan</strong>, Raman spectroscopy: Potential for detecting tissue coagulation during laser therapy, in Biomedical Optics, OSA Technical Digest, Optical Society of America, paper BTuF46, 2008.&nbsp;<strong><a href="http://www.opticsinfobase.org/abstract.cfm?URI=BIOMED-2008-BTuF46" target="_blank">abstract</a></strong></p>

	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>8</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>Content</title>
		<div><img height="225" width="300" align="right" alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/Michelle.JPG" />Welcome to the <strong>Biomedical Optics Research Group</strong>.</div>
		<p>&nbsp;</p>
		<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
	</node>
	<node>
		<nid>6</nid>
		<type>book</type>
		<title>The Research</title>
		<p><span>The <strong>Biomedical Optics Project</strong> consists of three research foci:<span><img height="338" width="450" align="right" alt="" src="/biomedical-optics/sites/discoveryspace.upei.ca.biomedical-optics/files/DSC00155.JPG" /></span></span></p>
		<div><span>&bull; design, develop and fabricate an optical fiber platform that will enable the effective delivery and assessment of laser thermal therapies.</span></div>
		<div>&nbsp;</div>
		<div><span>&bull; develop new fiber optic instruments that are sensitive to changes in tissue structure and hemodynamics for improved tissue characterization.</span></div>
		<div>&nbsp;</div>
		<div><span>&bull; develop new functionality to Seno Medical&rsquo;s optoacoustic platform for cancer therapy guidance and assessment, and with this new knowledge, work to develop a next generation optoacoustic system capable of large animal and human imaging in a clinical setting.</span></div>
		<div>&nbsp;</div>
		<p><span>The project will be carried out over a five-year period. The project will be based at UPEI in Charlottetown, PEI. The initial prototyping work will be carried out at UPEI, and further development of prototypes will be carried out in partner facilities in Slemon Park and San Antonio, Texas. As technologies are developed they will be first tested and validated through pre-human clinical trials conducted at UPEI&rsquo;s Atlantic Veterinary College, and then used in human clinical trials carried out at the Princess Margaret Hospital in Toronto. </span></p>
		<p>&nbsp;</p>
	</node>
</node_export>
